Adolph Bolm Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
- Articles (Box 2, 5)
  - Articles about Bolm (Box 2, 5)
    - "Adolph Bolm" (Russian) (Box-folder 2/27)
    - Bolm press notices (Box-folder 2/28)
    - Bolm press releases (Box-folder 2/29)
    - Photocopies of articles on Bolm (Box-folder 2/30)
    - Photocopies of press clippings (Box-folder 2/31, 5/7)
  - Articles by Bolm (Box 2)
    - "Art and Music," San Francisco Chronicle, March 8, 1936 (Box-folder 2/32)
    - "European ballet master gives his impressions of Native American dance," San Francisco Chronicle, September 20, 1936 (Box-folder 2/33)
    - Screen Guild Magazine, "On with the dance," July 1937 (Box-folder 2/34)
    - Photocopies of articles by Bolm (Box-folder 2/35)
- Correspondence (Box 2-3)
  The bulk of the Correspondence series includes letters and notes from composer John Alden Carpenter from 1932 to 1950. The letters discuss artists, including Stravinsky, ballets, and music from the period. For example, in letters from 1942 and 1940 respectively, Carpenter writes positively about Anthony Tudor’s ballets Pillar of Fire and Jardin aux Lilacs. He also writes about Walt Disney’s plan to make a sequel to the 1940 film Fantasia, which was to feature Carpenter’s Adventures in a Perambulator, Stravinsky’s Firebird and Petrouchka, and Prokofiev’s Peter and the Wolf. In addition, the series contains telegrams sent to Bolm regarding his engagements with different ballet companies, miscellaneous Christmas cards, and correspondence to Bolm’s biographer, John Dougherty.
  - Carpenter, John Alden to Beata and Adolph Bolm (Box 2)
    - 1932 (Box-folder 2/36)
    - 1933 (Box-folder 2/37)
    - 1934 (Box-folder 2/38)
    - 1935 (Box-folder 2/39)
    - 1936 (Box-folder 2/40)
    - 1937 (Box-folder 2/41)
    - 1938 (Box-folder 2/42)
    - 1939 (Box-folder 2/43)
    - 1940 (Box-folder 2/44)
    - 1941 (Box-folder 2/45)
    - 1942 (Box-folder 2/46)
    - 1943 (Box-folder 2/47)
    - 1944 (Box-folder 2/48)
    - 1945 (Box-folder 2/49)
    - 1946 (Box-folder 2/50)
    - 1947 (Box-folder 2/51)
    - 1948 (Box-folder 2/52)
    - 1949 (Box-folder 2/53)
    - 1950 (Box-folder 2/54)
    - date unknown (Box-folder 2/55)
  - Carpenter to Olaf Bolm (Box-folder 2/56)
  - Correspondence from Beata Bolm to Edna McRae, (Photocopies) (Box-folder 2/60)
  - Correspondence to Beata Bolm (Box 2)
    - From Ellen Carpenter (Box-folder 2/57)
    - From Ginny Carpenter Hill (Box-folder 2/58)
    - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 2/59)
  - Correspondence to Stravinsky from others (Box-folder 2/61)
  - Photocopies of Bolm's correspondence (Box-folder 2/62)
  - Telegrams to Bolm (Box-folder 2/63)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 3)
    - Dougherty, John, (Biographer) (Box-folder 3/1)
    - Christmas cards (Box-folder 3/2)
    - unknown (Box-folder 3/3)
- Business Papers (Box 3-5)
  The Business Papers series includes Bolm’s travel documents from Russia, France, and the United States. It also includes his passport, registration certificates for the U.S., and certificate of naturalization. In addition, it contains Bolm’s address book from the 1920s and several contracts and financial agreements with various companies, including the Ballet Theatre.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Adolph Bolm (Box 3-5)
    - Address book from the 1920s (Box-folder 3/4)
    - Bolm travel documents for U.S. (Box-folder 3/5)
    - Contracts and financial agreements (Box-folder 3/6)
    - Declaration of arrival to U.S., 1920, 1921 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - French identification card and certificate, 1920 (Box-folder 3/8)
    - Funeral and life insurance documents, 1951 (Box-folder 3/9)
    - Letters and notes (Box-folder 3/10)
    - Notice from Russian Consulate (Box-folder 3/11)
    - Russian passport (Box-folder 3/12)
    - Russian travel documents, 1895, 1915 (Box-folder 4/17)
    - Spanish travel document (Box-folder 3/13)
    - United States Certificate of Naturalization, 1925 (Box-folder 4/16)
    - United States passport, 1925 (Box-folder 5/8)
    - United States passport, 1950 (Box-folder 3/14)
    - United States registration papers, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 3/15)
  - Beata Bolm (Box 3-4)
    - U.S. Certificate of Naturalization, 1926 (Box-folder 3/16)
    - Russian passport, 1925 (Box-folder 4/18)
    - Miscellaneous: Bolm stationery (Box-folder 3/17)
- Anna Pavlova Materials (Box 3)
  The Anna Pavlova Materials series includes a photo of Pavlova and Bolm; telegrams sent by Bolm to others expressing his sorrow at the news of her death in 1931; an homage written by Bolm about Pavlova; and letters written by Pavlova’s family or staff that detail her passing.
  - Bolm's hommage to Pavlova after her death (Box-folder 3/18)
  - Bolm's telegrams about Pavlova's death (Box-folder 3/19)
  - Letter to Bolm informing him of Pavlova's death, 1931 (Box-folder 3/20)
  - Photograph of Bolm and Pavlova (Box-folder 3/21)
  - Letters to Bolm, in Russian, on Pavlova's stationery, from different people (Box-folder 3/22)
  - Obituary of Pavlova in Russian (Box-folder 3/23)
- Writings (Box 3)
  The Writings series contains unpublished documents about Bolm by various authors, including notes and drafts for a Bolm biography by Rosalind Shaffer de Mille. The series also includes Bolm’s recollections of his education in St. Petersburg as told to Vera Carpary, and memories meant to be used in a film by Anna Leontovich. In addition, there is material written by de Mille about a film project on Marie Taglioni, and the making of La Sylphide. A copy of Stravinsky’s original libretto for Apollo is also included.
  - Bolm's recollections and short biographies (Box-folder 3/24)
  - Eugene Berman article: Saturday Review, "Hail Don Giovanni, Farewell Theater," October 1957, p. 45-65, (Photocopy) (Box-folder 3/25)
  - Lillian Michell outline and bibliography for Bolm, 1976 (Box-folder 3/26)
  - Rosalind Shaffer De Mille's notes for Bolm biography, (Photocopies) (Box-folder 3/27)
  - Shaffer outline and drafts for Bolm biography, 1951-1952 (Box-folder 3/28)
  - Shaffer's Taglioni project: synopsis and script, (Photocopies) (Box-folder 3/29)
  - Sources and quotes on Bolm (Box-folder 3/30)
  - Stravinsky's Apollo Musagète libretto, 1943, (Photocopy) (Box-folder 3/31)
- Artwork (Box 5-6, Mapcase 3)
  The Artwork series contains five pieces of original works of art. There are three costume designs by Jane Berlandina for Bolm’s 1934 ballet Danse Noble for the San Francisco Opera. The series also includes Nikolai Roerich’s painting of the peasant and dancing bear from the ballet Petrouchka (the design for the 1911 Fokine version was by Alexandre Benois) and Troy Kinney’s painting of Bolm in Prince Igor.
  - Jane Berlandina's costume designs for Danse Noble (Box-folder 5/9-11)
  - Troy Kinney painting of Adolf Bolm as Chief Warrior in Prince Igor (Box-folder 6/4)
  - Nikolai Roerich painting of Peasant and Dancing Bear from Petrouchka (Mapcase-drawer 3/1)
- Commemorative Items and Music Scores (Box 3-4, 8)
  The Commemorative Items and Music Scores series includes several miscellaneous items, including two published scores by Stravinsky (one with an inscription), and composer Carlos Salzedo’s piano prelude written in honor of the birth of Bolm’s son in 1920. In addition, there are two autograph books containing composers' signatures, including Dmitri Shostakovich's, and an envelope bearing Stravinsky’s honorary stamp from 1982.
  - Commemorative Items (Box 3-4, 8)
    - Autograph books (Box 8)
    - Adolph Bolm Memorial Gift to the Exceptional Children's Foundation, Los Angeles, CA, 1951 (Box-folder 3/32)
    - Igor Stravinsky stamp, Great Americans Series, 1982 (Box-folder 3/33)
    - Studies from the Russian Ballet by E.O. Hoppe, Book cover, with table of contents on back. (Box-folder 4/22)
  - Published Music Scores (Box 4)
    - Circus Polka, by Igor Stravinsky, 1942 (Box-folder 4/19)
    - Prelude to Olaf Bolm on the occasion of his birth, by Carlos Salzedo, 1920 (Box-folder 4/20)
    - "Star Spangled Banner," harmonized and set for chorus by Igor Stravinsky, 1941 (Box-folder 4/21)